<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ripping-up of Sir John Presbyter's garment, or, The Ground-work of schism laid open to all true Protestant readers, &amp;c</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38037</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17163188</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17163188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106065</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106065)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1099:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Ripping-up of Sir John Presbyter's garment, or, The Ground-work of schism laid open to all true Protestant readers, &amp;c</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Tom the joyner.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tom, --  the joyner.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106065:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Ripping-up of <hi>Sir Iohn Preſbyter's Garment:</hi> OR, THE Ground-work of Schiſm, Laid open to all true <hi>Proteſtant Readers,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Shall not ſtop your deſires by an Epiſtle, but fall plainly to the Matter, which I hope may not only divert, but convert thee, if you are not already Conformable; for know, thoſe foul and damnable <hi>Presbytical practices</hi> which are daily working, are not inviſible to the All-ſeeing God, though for a time they may be ſo to men.</p>
            <p>I know their preſent deſigns are ſtrengthned and encouraged by the ſame Party, who made the late Inſurrection in <hi>Scotland;</hi> they think (and ſtick not to ſpeak it too) that by compulſion the King muſt yield to their demands: but let them not be deceived, for howſoever in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſome thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtrong enough to reſiſt their Prince, yet I thank God they are not ſo popular here, but the King's Laws and Authority is able to overtake them: And aſſured they may be, that theſe their inſolent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions againſt the King and his Intereſt, will make their Faction be more narrowly look'd into; for certainly they have not any ſpark of God's Grace, nor Loyalty to their King, and ſo are become the Children of Sin and Rebellion: wherefore behold their proceedings, and judge them accordingly.</p>
            <p>You may perceive how that Sect, ſince the firſt beginning of it, (which was but in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Reign) hath proceeded from evil to worſe by innumerable degrees: at firſt they did only manifeſt a <hi>diſlike</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> and ſome Ceremonies uſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as liking better the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Geneva;</hi> which was deſired by Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and that cunningly enough for the State of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, which being Popular, could not brook any other but that which is Popular alſo. And yet I muſt tell you, Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> wanted nothing of a Biſhop, but only the Title; for the Church of <hi>Geneva</hi> is not a <hi>Parochial,</hi> but <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Church, conſiſting of divers Pariſhes, which make up one great <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and he all the days of his life was Moderator thereof: And ſo likewiſe Mr. <hi>Beza,</hi> for ten years after the others death, held the ſame place of Government; until <hi>Danaeus</hi> ſet him beſide the Cuſhion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the Precedency to go by turns. In the next place, from <hi>diſlike</hi> they proceeded to <hi>contempt</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal Government;</hi> and this (if you will believe St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>) hath been the very beginning of all Hereſies and Schiſms, <hi>Initia Haereticorum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; ortus Schiſmaticorum haec ſunt, ut praepoſitum ſuperbo tumore contemnant.</hi> And again, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Schiſmata &amp; Haereſes orta ſunt niſi dum Epiſcopus qui unus eſt, &amp; Eccleſia praeeſt, ſuperbâ quorundam praeſumptione contemnitur: &amp; homo dignatione Dei honoratus ab indignis hominibus judicatur.</hi> In the third place, from <hi>contempt</hi> they did proceed unto open <hi>diſobedience</hi> unto all the Orders of the Church, and (like thoſe of whom <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaks) would be pleaſed with nothing but what did proceed from their own deviſing, eſteeming him the Holieſt man, who could find moſt Faults. From <hi>diſobedience</hi> they did proceed unto <hi>Schiſm</hi> and open <hi>Separation,</hi> accounting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only to be the Brethren and Congregation of Chriſt, and all others who are not of their Faction to be the Children of this World. From <hi>Schiſm</hi> they proceed to <hi>Hereſie;</hi> for it is moſt true which St. <hi>Jerome</hi> did obſerve, that <hi>Omne Schiſmagignit ſibi Haereſin,</hi> every Schiſm doth deviſe unto it ſelf an Hereſie, ſome falſe Doctrine or other, to maintain their Separation: And theſe men have deviſed not a few, and ſome that have been condemned by Ancient Councils and Fathers; as namely, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> reckons among the condemn'd Hereſies of <hi>Aerius,</hi> that he maintained there was no difference between a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and that all ſet <hi>Faſts</hi> are unlawful, Jewiſh and Superſtitious. And is not ſuch the Doctrine of theſe men? But their <hi>diſobedience, Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> has again drawn them even to the brink of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> where the hopes of ſome immediate proceedings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> has ſtopt their Carreer for the preſent: But I am deceiv'd if they have not yet a farther Journey to go, and that they no eaſe can find till arrived at the ſecond part of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> from which their hearts now differ but little; and if you'l but read the Hiſtory of the late Civil Wars, you will find their proceedings were then more moderate than now they are. This is the juſt Judgment of God, that they who out-run the limits of his infinite goodneſs, and the mercy of their moſt clement and gracious King, ſhould alſo run out of their own wits, and into the very Lake of Perdition and Puritaniſm.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106065:2"/>
            <p>I beſeech all good Proteſtants in time to conſider their ways and proceedings, and how they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to caſt miſts before our eyes, whilſt their Rebellious practices run to the point they ſo earneſtly pray for: I proteſt their groſs Hypocriſie in matters of Religion, and their baſe injurious dealing with Kings, who are God's Vice-gerents here on Earth, is moſt unpardonable, both which I have obſerv'd by their Doctrine and Practices, and will now give you a brief taſte of both.</p>
            <p>As for their Doctrine, we know they would, if they durſt, take from the King all Authority in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, and will not allow him to do thoſe things which the good <hi>Kings of Judah;</hi> and the Godly Emperors of the Primitive Church did; nay they will not accept or allow of ſo much as one Member of Parliament, recommended by the King, nor His Majeſty to make any Laws concerning matters of outward Order and Polity; nay they have gone farther, allowing and encouraging Subjects to reſiſt their Prince, and are now on the ſame ſtep of Rebellion, and that next door to being done by force of Arms; and in ſome caſes to depoſe him, nay and condemn him as a Tyrant: And though the Godlieſt Prince in the World, by them he muſt be eſteemed ſo, for it much pleaſes the <hi>Presbyter</hi> to declare him ſuch; ſo that according to this account, Kings muſt be in a far worſe caſe under <hi>Presbytery,</hi> than ever they were under the <hi>Pope.</hi> This is their Doctrine; and now I will ſhew you their Practice: Firſt, thoſe of the ſame fraternity in <hi>Scotland,</hi> how they dealt with King <hi>James;</hi> they perſecuted him in his Mothers womb, and when he came unto ripe years, they would not ſuffer him to enjoy one quiet day, by their Seditious practices: of a great many, I will cull out ſome of their Attempts, which are moſt notorious. Firſt, when the Ring-leaders of that Faction had concluded the State of Biſhops to be unlawful, they ſent their Commiſſioners unto the King, commanding him and his Council under pain of Excommunication to put them down. Secondly, when King <hi>James</hi> was taken Priſoner at <hi>Ruthen,</hi> by their Treachery, intending thereby to enforce His Majeſty to their own ends, he being happily delivered from them, did with the conſent of his Three Eſtates in Parliament, declare it to be a Treaſonable Fact; but the Seditious Miniſters being aſſembled, and taking themſelves to be the Supreme Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, did pronounce that Treaſon to be moſt juſt and lawful: but they being farther examined on that point, declin'd his Majeſties Authority, alledging he was no Judge over them in Church-matters: all this and much more you may read in King <hi>James</hi> his Declaration, printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1585. When the Earl of <hi>Bothwell</hi> was in the act of Rebellion againſt the King, and had divers times attempted to take away his Majeſties Life, there were by the Miniſters great Collections made to maintain the ſaid Earl in his Rebellion. Afterwards when the <hi>Gowries</hi> conſpired againſt his Majeſty, and he miraculouſly reſcued by the Valour of his Servants, his Majeſty deſired there might be a Publick Thankſgiving throughout the Realm for his deliverance; but thoſe of that Faction did plainly ſay, they neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd the King or his Nobles, nor that ever there was ſuch a Conſpiracy; but that it was a Plot of the King to murder the <hi>Gowries.</hi> One thing I cannot omit, how they call'd a National Aſſembly to be held in <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> the King ſuſpecting the event, and having long before by Act of Parliament, all Authority in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, ſent to inhibit them by Proclamation, but they would not deſiſt: whereupon ſome were apprehended, indicted and found guilty of High Treaſon; yet that merciful Prince did neither take Life nor Goods from any of them, only cauſed ſix to be baniſhed, who upon the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of their offence, were admitted to their former ſtations again: and yet the Tincture of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion would not out, for the Succeſſors of thoſe very perſons are to this day ſome of the principal Firebrands in a new, but worſe Conſpiracy; witneſs the late Inſurrection in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the moſt inhuman and barbarous murder of the Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I given you a brief account of their Doctrine and Practices concerning the oppoſing of Kings; but leſt this ſhould be thought a National ſin, and ſo <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upbraid her Siſter <hi>Samaria,</hi> I will ſhew unto you, that they of the ſame Fraternity in <hi>England,</hi> have not at all ſwerved from the tracks of their <hi>Scotch</hi> Predeceſſors, but rather are become more dangerous and bloudy in their deſigns; witneſs King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed memory, how barbarouſly they dealt with his Majeſty, and the whole Line-Royal, by their means to be baniſhed: And yet when God of his infinite mercy had re-call'd our gracious King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and ſet him on his Throne, in the ſpite of thoſe his mortal Enemies, he of his great goodneſs and compaſſion extended his gracious Pardon to all ſuch as were any ways concerned againſt him only ſome few excepted; and yet even from that very day have theſe wicked Varlets run on in the old path of Rebellion and Conſpiracy, and are even at this juncture ſtudying ways to dethrone his moſt Sacred Majeſty: and yet theſe are the things we ſilly Proteſtants take for Saints, and cannot diſcover them to be of the Black Robe, until we come to dance to the ſecond part of the ſame Tune they play'd in 41. when then perhaps 'tis too late. For if ever there were Devils transformed into Saints, 'tis now, and thruſt in under the Skirt of <hi>John Presbyter</hi>'s Cloak, who with the pretence of Sanctity, labour to bring all manner of diſcord into the Church, and conſuſion into the Kingdom, and the Government thereof; as if the Regulating of Church and State, wholly reſted with the Rabble Faction. By the ſum of all Hiſtories it is plain, theſe People envy all Kings whatſoever, and ſo get Gods promiſe made to his Church, <hi>That Kings ſhould be her Nurſing-fathers, and Queens her Nurſing mothers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what need I repeat matters of old? For the Children are worſe than the Fathers, and their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent devices doth ſurpaſs all the Iniquities of their Fathers, and will make thoſe of old to be forgotten: And yet theſe are the people who ſwear to be good examples to us of all Godlineſs, Soberneſs; and in fine, of every Duty they owe to God and Man. Now pray Reader gueſs what Godlineſs, Soberneſs,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106065:2"/>or Righteouſheſs, has or can be in ſuch proceedings: they now begin to be weary with aſſaulting us with their Tongues, which are ſharper than Arrows, and with their Pens, which write Treaſon in as plain a ſtile, as their Parſons in their Pulpits teach it; and are come (as <hi>Tertulltan</hi> ſays) <hi>a ſtilo ad mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeram,</hi> from words to blows or very near the matter: which puts us to ſay, with <hi>Bernard, Leones eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus, ſed incidimus in Dracones,</hi> we eſcap'd the mouths of Lions, but have fallen into a Den of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons; for theſe ſure are <hi>Cerastes</hi> fiery flying Dragons. But it would be well if their madneſs ſtay there, for they not only do wrong unto God in the higheſt degree, but would touch his Anointed, by entring into a mutual <hi>League and Covenant,</hi> by incenſing and Arming his Subjects againſt him, taking Oaths of them to ſtand by, and maintain the Cauſe, and endeavouring to ſow diſcord amongſt thoſe of Loyal Souls, to the confuſion of our gracious King and his Government. Good God! can ſuch call themſelves Chriſtians that do theſe things? can they warrant this out of Gods Word, which commands to <hi>obey our King,</hi> and that <hi>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> even then when all Kings were Enemies to Chriſtianity and Religion? or have they any Examples for ſuch proceedings out of pious Antiquity? The Chriſtians in the Primitive Church, when they were led as Sheep to the ſlaughter, and ſuffer'd the moſt exquiſite Torments that could be devis'd, yet would never take Arms to reſiſt their Prince, but put on this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution <hi>Arma nostra preces &amp; lachrymae:</hi> Yea, when thoſe perſecuting Emperors had occaſion of War againſt the barbarous Nations, the Chriſtians were the Emperors beſt and moſt faithful Souldiers, ſo terrible unto their Enemies, that they were call'd <hi>the Thundering Legions:</hi> And St. <hi>Austin</hi> doth highly commend them for their faithful Service unto the Heathen Emperors, who did moſt cruelly ſpill their Bloud, only for their profeſſion of Chriſt. And let no man ſay, it was for want of Power, that they did not defend themſelves by Arms; for it is well known, that if they had thought it lawful to reſiſt the Emperor, they were of that number, power and reſolution, that they might have ſhaken the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the whole Empire. But now it ſeems our <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> of whom I ſpeak, have learned another ſort of Doctrine, and think they are bound to ſtand to the defence of their dread Soveraign, his Perſon and Authority, in defence of the true Religion, (as they expreſs it in the Confeſſion of their Faith, whereunto they all are obliged to ſwear;) ſo that they do plainly inſinuate, they are no farther bound to defend the Kings Perſon and Authority, than he doth ſtand in the defence of the true Religion, and that only muſt be accounted ſo, which they themſelves beſt like of: If the King will not maintain that, then they are freed from their Allegiance. Wherein they have more then juſtified the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> for about the beginning of the late Civil Wars, a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> wrote a Book in defence of the Loyalty of their Order, alledging that Proteſtants had allowed the Rebellion of Subjects againſt Princes, and gives inſtance for the ſame in <hi>Buchanan, Knox,</hi> and <hi>Goodman:</hi> and now it fears me, that ere it be long another <hi>Jeſuit</hi> may publiſh a Book, to prove that the late Inſurrection in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was a greater Rebellion then was the Popiſh Plot: For if matters are carefully inſpected, we may find our <hi>Puritain Brethren</hi> have engaged a great part of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and many who know not what the matter means; ſo that this may be called the <hi>common ſin of that Sect,</hi> whereas the other cannot-be charged upon the Religion of the <hi>Papists.</hi> But perhaps you will ſay, it is Religion that moveth them: What! did ever the true Religion allow of Rebellion? <hi>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum:</hi> I know they pretend the defence of the National Confeſſion of their Church, and the Oath received by their Forefathers in the year 1581. by the Kings example and commandment; but if it be ſo, I will ſubſcribe their <hi>Covenant</hi> alſo, which is the greateſt Curſe I can lay upon my mortal Enemy.</p>
            <p>And now I have taken from them all pretences of Religion, which is not fit to be a Mask for ſuch Villany; I will gueſs what are the true cauſes that ſet them on work, not uſing light conjectures, but building on more then probable grounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That which ſets the Clergy on work, is <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> which (as St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſays) did build the City of the Devil: it is pride, ſingularity, ambition, and the deſire of popular applauſe; they cannot endure to acknowledg a Biſhop, eſteeming themſelves men of greater gifts and perfections. This pride has been the occaſion of many Hereſies in the Church, as will evidently appear unto thoſe who read the Hiſtories of <hi>Arius,</hi> coveting the Biſhoprick of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> of <hi>Donatus,</hi> labouring to have been Biſhop of <hi>Carthage;</hi> of <hi>Novatus,</hi> deſiring a Biſhoprick in <hi>Italy;</hi> and divers others I could name, who affected theſe Honourable places, and receiving their ſeveral Foyls, when through ambition they could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what they ſought for in the Church, they laboured to gain Honour another way. I could alſo tell you of many who are now Ring-leaders of the Faction here in <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Pemberton, Stretton, Alſop, Whitaker,</hi> and divers others, who publickly preach Sedition and Rebellion in their ſeveral Meetings, and the King to be a Conſpirator againſt himſelf: If ſuch can be the true Doctrine of Chriſt, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it is, God have mercy on all Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That which ſets the Lay-men on work, is <hi>Convetouſneſs:</hi> amongſt whom not a few would gladly prey (as their predeceſſors have done) upon the Abbies, Church-Lands, Biſhopricks, Tithes, and Church-Duties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And they in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they are of the ſame Stock, ſo conſequently they are alſo of the ſame mind: And when they hear any ſpeak againſt <hi>Popery, Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Catheral Churches,</hi> nay againſt the <hi>King</hi> or his <hi>Government,</hi> (for there's enow dare do it) how it pleaſes and tickles their Ears, looking for the like prey they formerly had? Theſe dark-Lanthorn Saints have already in their hearts devoured the Government both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and value not Religion, ſo they may but get the Spoil; nay I am confident they would have been content to have Crucified our Bleſſed Saviour, ſo they might but have had his Garment. Our Age is full of Bloud-thirſty Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106065:3"/>whoſe hearts and inclinations are full of <hi>Perjury, Blaſphemy, Murther,</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> in all degrees, and are ſtill yawning after a prey to fill the bottomleſs Sacks of their greedy Appetites with: And although it be to their perpetual ſhame and infamy, yet would they purchaſe a ſecond <hi>Field of bloud,</hi> ſo little they value the name of an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> which once was beyond parallel, and is now even among the <hi>Turks</hi> become a ſcorn, and muſt be daſht in the Teeth with <hi>Murthering their King,</hi> though never ſo loyal in heart. Thus have theſe Vipers made our whole Nation odious to the World by their venomous Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I may more then probably conjecture, that they have another aim, even ſuch as was <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams:</hi> when he had drawn away the Ten Tribes from the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> he ſaid in his heart, <hi>If the people go up to Jeruſalem to worſhip, their hearts will return again unto their Lord Rehoboam;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he erected two Golden Calves, and ſaid unto the people, <hi>It is too far for you to go up to Jeruſalem; theſe are the Gods that brought you up out of the Land of Egypt:</hi> So theſe intending to draw away the King's Subjects from their Obedience, and perceiving that if they ſhould joyn with His Majeſties good Subjects, in the true and orderly worſhip of God, that their hearts would return again unto their Lord the King; they have deviſed an Idol of their own brain, like <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Calves, even their <hi>Presbyterial Diſcipline,</hi> and cry that up as the only true worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>And yet I hold them not all to be alike guilty, but that many, yea the far greateſt part, have not as yet learned the depth of Satan: we may diſtinguiſh them into two degrees; The firſt ſort are, they who are the principal Contrivers and Actors, and the Seducers of others; for ſuch there is no excuſe to be made, therefore I ſhall leave them as wild Aſſes, to be ſpoken with in the mouth of their affliction: The ſecond ſort, and the far greater number, are the Seduced, which are like thoſe 200 which followed <hi>Abſalom</hi> out of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> knowing nothing of his Treaſon; theſe have been drawn to dance after their Pipe, though they underſtood not the Tune, yet they are carried along with it, and all done under Godly pretences, for they are made to believe, that the very ſtate of Religion, Church, and Kingdom, do depend on the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and that they are all bound in Conſcience to defend the <hi>National Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> and the Oath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, ſworn by their Forefathers: beſides, it is with the people a very plauſible matter, to hear them depraved that are in Authority, but eſpecially to underſtand of any Liberty or Power, which may apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto themſelves. Furthermore alſo, it is not unknown to any of Judgment, how much the profeſſion of extraordinary Zeal, doth work with the un-thinking Multitude; when they ſee men go ſimply in the Streets, bowing down their heads like Bulruſhes, though their inward parts burn with deceit, wringing their Necks awry, fetching deep ſighs, and turning up the whites of their Eyes, as though they were in ſome intollerable grief; and finally, make long Prayers, under colour whereof they would not only devour the Houſes of the Fatherleſs and Widows, but the Married people alſo, in ſo much that none can eſcape their violence. Lord, what Tyrannical hands are we like to fall into! can theſe men produce me one Text of Scripture, to ſupport or verifie their proceedings? No not one; for thoſe Holy Laws admit not of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, Sacriledge, Diſobedience to a lawful Authority,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion againſt Princes:</hi> theſe are the very Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries of Chriſtendom, as if they had come to ſet Fire on the Earth; not gentle and mild, but are more auſtere in their carriage than ever was <hi>Cato;</hi> they are known to be the moſt rigid Cenſurers of others, whilſt they applaud their own Vitious Actions in the higheſt; they eaſily eſpy the Mote in their Brothers eye, but cannot endure to hear of the Beam in their own.</p>
            <p>All this have I done, to detect theſe men and their proceedings, to the end that I might draw from amongſt them, all that pretend to Chriſtianity, or any the leaſt Moral Virtues, if there be any ſuch uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: for who would follow their ſteps, whoſe <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> whoſe <hi>Bond</hi> is <hi>Perjury,</hi> whoſe <hi>Badge</hi> is <hi>Rebellion?</hi> Therefore come out from among them, and partake not in their ſins, leſt you receive alſo of the Plagues God has prepared for them, and think not to halt thus between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Baal;</hi> neither do thou fear their power, for howſoever they proſper for a time, it is but a Summer Storm, and let them be aſſured it will not be long before their turn of Sufferings come about: For that God by whoſe Power <hi>Kings Reign,</hi> will give ſtrength unto his King, and <hi>exalt the horn of his Anointed;</hi> he will ſcatter the people that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in War, and make their hearts to melt, and their joynts to tremble. This I proteſt to God I ſpeak out of the great grief of my heart, and the very anguiſh of my Soul; when I conſider the dreadful after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps that are like to enſue, it fears me, that our Sins are come to a full maturity, and that we are ripe for God's Sickle to reap us. I dare not ſay, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that I could wiſh my ſelf <hi>Anathema,</hi> or <hi>ſeparated from Chriſt</hi> for my Country-men; but I do ſay with all ſincerity of heart, that I could be content my Life were given in a Sacrifice, ſo that could procure the Peace and Unity of our Nation, that ſo my King and his good Subjects may be preſerved from the moſt damnable havock <hi>John Presbyter</hi> deſigns to make amongſt us: Therefore I beſeech all you of good will to joyn with me, by applying our endeavours for quenching of this Fire, (which as yet is only to be found by its Smoak) let all of us be inſtant with God in Prayer, lifting up our hearts and hands to the Heavens, and beſeech him who is the Author of Peace, that he will be pleaſed to open the eyes of that wicked People, and turn their hearts, that they may acknowledge their Duty to God, and perform their Obedience to his Vice-gerent: This is the true Prayer of honeſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tom the Joyner.</signed>
               <pb facs="tcp:106065:3"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
